let's talk about what is never going to change about storytelling. Shonda Rhimes: What's never going to change. Obviously, I think good stories are never going to change, the need for people to gather together and exchange their stories and to talk about the things that feel universal, the idea that we all feel a compelling need to watch stories, to tell stories, to share stories --
hablemos de lo que nunca cambiará en la narración. Shonda Rhimes: Lo que nunca cambiará. Obviamente, creo que las buenas historias nunca cambiarán, la necesidad de las personas de juntarse e intercambiar historias y hablar de las cosas trascendentales, la idea de que todos sentimos una imperiosa necesidad de conocer historias, de contarlas, de compartirlas...
sort of the gathering around the campfire to discuss the things that tell each one of us that we are not alone in the world. Those things to me are never going to change. That essence of storytelling is never going to change. CS: OK. In preparation for this conversation, I checked in with Susan Lyne, who was running ABC Entertainment when you were working on "Grey's Anatomy" -- SR: Yes. CS: And she said that there was this indelible memory she had of your casting process, where without discussing it with any of the executives, you got people coming in to read for your scripts, and every one of them was the full range of humanity, you did not type anyone in any way, and that it was completely surprising. So she said, in addition to retraining the studio executives, you also, she feels, and I think this is -- I agree, retrained the expectations of the American TV audience. So what else does the audience not yet realize that it needs? SR: What else does it not yet realize? Well, I mean, I don't think we're anywhere near there yet. I mean, we're still in a place in which we're far, far behind what looks like the real world in actuality. I wasn't bringing in a bunch of actors who looked very different from one another simply because I was trying to make a point, and I wasn't trying to do anything special. It never occurred to me that that was new, different or weird. I just brought in actors because I thought they were interesting and to me, the idea that it was completely surprising to everybody --
de reunirnos en torno a una fogata para hablar de las cosas que nos indican que no estamos solos en el mundo. Para mí, esas cosas nunca cambiarán. La esencia de la narración nunca cambiará. CS: Bien. Cuando me preparaba para esta conversación, contacté a Susan Lyne, que estaba a cargo de ABC Entertainment cuando trabajabas en "Anatomía de Grey". SR: Sí. CS: Y ella me dijo que tenía un recuerdo imborrable de tu proceso de selección, en el que, sin discutirlo con ninguno de los ejecutivos, invitaste a gente a venir a leer tus guiones, y en ellos había todo tipo de personas, no consultaste con nadie en ninguna forma, y eso fue totalmente sorprendente. Ella me dijo que además de volver a enseñar algo nuevo a los ejecutivos, y a ti, ella siente, y creo que es... concuerdo, es cambiar las expectativas de la audiencia televisiva de EE.UU. ¿De qué otra cosa la audiencia no se ha dado cuenta que necesita? SR: ¿De qué más no se ha dado cuenta aún? Bien, bueno... No creo que hayamos llegado a ese punto aún. Es decir, todavía estamos en un punto muy, muy lejano de lo que el mundo es en realidad. No es que trajera a un montón de actores que lucieran muy diferentes unos de otros solo porque tratara de demostrar algo, y tampoco trataba de hacer algo especial. Nunca se me ocurrió que fuera algo nuevo, diferente o extraño. Solo traje a los actores porque pensé que eran interesantes y para mí, el que fuera tan sorprendente para todos...
I didn't know that for a while. I just thought: these are the actors I want to see play these parts. I want to see what they look like if they read. We'll see what happens. So I think the interesting thing that happens is that when you look at the world through another lens, when you're not the person normally in charge of things, it just comes out a different way. CS: So you now have this big machine that you run, as a titan -- as you know, last year when she gave her talk -- she's a titan. So what do you think is going to happen as we go on? There's a huge amount of money involved in producing these shows. While the tools of making stories have gone and gotten greatly democratized, there's still this large distribution: people who rent networks, who rent the audience to advertisers and make it all pay. How do you see the business model changing now that anyone can be a storyteller? SR: I think it's changing every day. I mean, the rapid, rapid change that's happening is amazing. And I feel -- the panic is palpable, and I don't mean that in a bad way. I think it's kind of exciting. The idea that there's sort of an equalizer happening, that sort of means that anybody can make something, is wonderful. I think there's some scary in the idea that you can't find the good work now. There's so much work out there. I think there's something like 417 dramas on television right now at any given time in any given place, but you can't find them. You can't find the good ones. So there's a lot of bad stuff out there because everybody can make something. It's like if everybody painted a painting. You know, there's not that many good painters. But finding the good stories, the good shows, is harder and harder and harder. Because if you have one tiny show over here on AMC and one tiny show over here over there, finding where they are becomes much harder. So I think that ferreting out the gems and finding out who made the great webisode and who made this, it's -- I mean, think about the poor critics who now are spending 24 hours a day trapped in their homes watching everything. It's not an easy job right now. So the distribution engines are getting more and more vast, but finding the good programming for everybody in the audience is getting harder. And unlike the news, where everything's getting winnowed down to just who you are, television seems to be getting -- and by television I mean anything you can watch, television shows on -- seems to be getting wider and wider and wider. And so anybody's making stories, and the geniuses are sometimes hidden. But it's going to be harder to find, and at some point that will collapse. People keep talking about peak TV. I don't know when that's going to happen. I think at some point it'll collapse a little bit and we'll, sort of, come back together. I don't know if it will be network television. I don't know if that model is sustainable. CS: What about the model
No lo supe sino después de un tiempo. Solo pensé: estos son los actores que quiero ver en estos papeles. Quiero ver cómo se ven leyéndolos. Veremos qué pasa. Así que, lo interesante es que si miras el mundo desde otro lente, cuando no eres la persona que normalmente está a cargo de las cosas, simplemente sale de otra manera. CS: Bien. Ahora maniobras esta gran máquina, como un titán -- como sabrán, dio una charla el año pasado -- ella es un titán. ¿Qué crees que va a pasar con el tiempo? Hay mucho dinero de por medio invertido en estos programas. Si bien las herramientas para crear historias se han democratizado, aún existe esta gran distribución: gente que alquila cadenas y audiencias a anunciantes y lo echan a andar. ¿Cómo cambiará el modelo de negocio ahora que cualquiera puede ser narrador? SR: Creo que siempre está cambiando. Es decir, es sorprendente lo rápido que está cambiando. Y siento -- el temor es palpable, y lo digo sin mala intención -- Creo que es emocionante. La idea de que haya algo como un igualador, el que cualquiera pueda hacer algo, es maravilloso. Creo que es aterradora la idea de que no se puede encontrar un buen empleo. Hay muy empleo. Creo que actualmente en la TV hay 417 series dramáticas en cualquier momento, en cualquier lugar, pero no puedes encontrarlas. No puedes encontrar las buenas. También hay cosas malas porque cualquiera puede hacer algo. Es como si todos hicieran una pintura. Como saben, no existen tantos buenos pintores. Pero encontrar buenas historias, buenos programas, es cada vez más difícil. Porque si solo hay un programita de cable por aquí y otro por allí y por allá, encontrar dónde están se vuelve más difícil. Creo que descubrir las joyas y averiguar quién hizo el gran webisodio, y quién hizo esto otro, es... pienso en los pobres críticos que pasan 24 horas al día atrapados en sus casas viendo de todo. No es un trabajo fácil hoy en día. Y los motores de distribución están volviéndose más y más vastos, pero encontrar buena programación para toda la audiencia se hace más difícil. Y a diferencia de las noticias, donde todo se reduce a solo quién eres, la TV parece estarse volviendo... y por TV me refiero a todo lo que se puede ver, programas de TV... todo parece más y más extenso. Así que cualquiera crea historias, y los genios a veces están escondidos. Pero va a ser más difícil encontrar, y en algún punto va a colapsar. La gente habla de la cima de la TV. No sé cuándo vaya a ocurrir. Creo que en algún punto va a colapsar un poco y entonces nos uniremos. No sé si vaya a ser una cadena de TV. No sé si ese modelo sea sostenible. CS: ¿Qué hay del modelo
that Amazon and Netflix are throwing a lot of money around right now. SR: That is true. I think it's an interesting model. I think there's something exciting about it. For content creators, I think there's something exciting about it. For the world, I think there's something exciting about it. The idea that there are programs now that can be in multiple languages with characters from all over the world that are appealing and come out for everybody at the same time is exciting. I mean, I think the international sense that television can now take on makes sense to me,
en el que Amazon y Netflix están invirtiendo tanto dinero ahora? SR: Es cierto. Creo que es un modelo interesante. Creo que hay algo de emocionante en ello. Para los creadores de contenido, creo que hay algo de emocionante. Para el mundo real, creo que hay algo emocionante en ello. El que haya programas ahora en múltiples idiomas con personajes de todo el mundo que son interesantes y que conectan con todos al mismo tiempo es emocionante. Es decir, creo que el sentido internacional que la TV asume ahora, tiene sentido para mí, que la programación pueda asumir el reto. La TV ha sido creada para la audiencia de EE.UU. Realizamos estos programas y luego los arrojan al mundo y esperamos lo mejor, en lugar de pensar que realmente eso no representa a EE.UU. Es decir, nos amamos y todo pero no me representa. Y deberíamos considerar que hay otros lugares en el mundo
that we should be interested in while we're telling stories. It makes the world smaller. I don't know. I think it pushes forward the idea that the world is a universal place, and our stories become universal things. We stop being other. CS: You've pioneered, as far as I can see, interesting ways to launch new shows, too. I mean, when you launched "Scandal" in 2012, there was this amazing groundswell of support on Twitter the likes of which nobody had seen before. Do you have any other tricks up your sleeve when you launch your next one? What do you think will happen in that regard? SR: We do have some interesting ideas. We have a show called "Still Star-Crossed" coming out this summer. We have some interesting ideas for that. I'm not sure if we're going to be able to do them in time. I thought they were fun. But the idea that we would live-tweet our show was really just us thinking that would be fun. We didn't realize that the critics would start to live-tweet along with us. But the fans -- getting people to be a part of it, making it more of a campfire -- you know, when you're all on Twitter together and you're all talking together, it is more of a shared experience, and finding other ways to make that possible and finding other ways to make people feel engaged is important. CS: So when you have all those different people making stories and only some of them are going to break through and get that audience somehow, how do you think storytellers will get paid? SR: I actually have been struggling with this concept as well. Is it going to be a subscriber model? Are people going to say, like, I'm going to watch this particular person's shows, and that's how we're going to do it? CS: I think we should buy a passport to Shondaland. Right? SR: I don't know about that, but yeah. That's a lot more work for me. I do think that there are going to be different ways, but I don't know necessarily.
que deberían interesarnos cuando contamos historias. Hace que el mundo sea más pequeño. No sé. Creo que promueve la idea de que el mundo es un lugar universal, y nuestras historias se vuelven universales. Dejamos de ser otro. CS: Tú innovaste, por lo que veo, maneras interesantes de lanzar nuevos programas también. Cuando lanzaste "Scandal" en 2012, hubo una oleada de apoyo en Twitter gustó como nunca antes. ¿Tienes otros ases bajo la manga para cuando lances el próximo? ¿Qué crees que pasará al respecto? SR: Sí tenemos unas ideas interesantes. Lanzaremos en verano un programa llamado "Still Star-Crossed". Tenemos algunas ideas interesantes. No sé si podremos hacerlas a tiempo. Me parecieron divertidas. Pero la idea de transmitirlo en vivo fue solo nuestra idea de que sería divertido. No nos percatamos de que los críticos comenzarían a tuitear en vivo también. Pero hacer que los seguidores fueran parte de ello -- hacerlo como un campamento -- como cuando todos están en Twitter y todos conversan juntos, es más bien una experiencia compartida y encontrar otras formas de hacer eso posible y encontrar otras formas de involucrar a las personas es importante. CS: Entonces, cuando todas esas personas hagan historias y solo algunas logren atraer a la audiencia de alguna forma ¿Cómo crees que se les pagará a los narradores? SR: De hecho, he pensado en eso también. ¿Va a ser un modelo de suscripción? ¿La gente va a mirar el programa de una persona en particular, y así lo haremos? CS: Quizá deberíamos comprar un pasaporte a Shondalandia, ¿no? SR: No lo sé, pero sí. Es mucho más trabajo para mí. Creo en verdad que habrá diferentes maneras, pero no necesariamente lo sé.
I mean, I'll be honest and say a lot of content creators are not necessarily interested in being distributors, mainly because what I dream of doing is creating content. I really love to create content. I want to get paid for it and I want to get paid the money that I deserve to get paid for it, and there's a hard part in finding that. But I also want it to be made possible for, you know, the people who work with me, the people who work for me,
Para ser honesta hay muchos creadores de contenido que no están necesariamente interesados en distribuir, en gran parte porque lo que sueño hacer es crear contenido. Realmente me fascina crear contenido. Que me paguen por ello y que me paguen lo que merezco por ello y es difícil encontrar eso. Pero también quiero hacerlo posible para la gente con quien trabajo, ¿sabes?, los que trabajan para mí,
everybody to sort of get paid in a way, and they're all making a living. How it gets distributed is getting harder and harder.
que a todos se les pague y puedan vivir de ello. El cómo distribuirlo se vuelve más y más difícil.
CS: How about the many new tools, you know, VR, AR ... I find it fascinating that you can't really binge-watch, you can't fast-forward in those things. What do you see as the future of those for storytelling? SR: I spent a lot of time in the past year just exploring those, getting lots of demonstrations and paying attention. I find them fascinating, mainly because I think that -- I think most people think of them for gaming, I think most people think of them for things like action, and I think that there is a sense of intimacy that is very present in those things, the idea that -- picture this, you can sit there and have a conversation with Fitz, or at least sit there while Fitz talks to you, President Fitzgerald Grant III, while he talks to you about why he's making a choice that he makes, and it's a very heartfelt moment. And instead of you watching a television screen, you're sitting there next to him, and he's having this conversation.
CS: ¿Qué hay de las nuevas herramientas, realidad virtual, realidad aumentada... me fascina que no se pueda hacer maratón televisivo, no se puede adelantar con esas herramientas. ¿Cuál crees que sea el futuro de estas tecnologías en la narración? SR: Pasé mucho tiempo el año pasado explorándolas, tuve muchas demostraciones y les presté atención. Me parecen fascinantes, en gran parte porque creo que... la mayoría de las personas piensan que son para jugar, la mayoría piensa que son para cosas de acción, y creo que hay un sentido de intimidad muy presente en esas cosas, la idea de que... imagina esto, puedes estar sentada aquí y conversar con Fitz, o al menos estar aquí mientras Fitz te habla, el presidente Fitzgerald Grant III, mientras él te cuenta por qué tomó la decisión que tomó, y es un momento conmovedor. Y en lugar de mirar una pantalla de TV, estás sentada junto a él, y él te está contando esto.
Now, you fall in love with the man while he's doing it from a television screen. Imagine sitting next to him, or being with a character like Huck who's about to execute somebody. And instead of having a scene where, you know, he's talking to another character very rapidly, he goes into a closet and turns to you and tells you, you know, what's going to happen and why he's afraid and nervous. It's a little more like theater, and I'm not sure it would work, but I'm fascinating by the concept of something like that and what that would mean for an audience. And to get to play with those ideas would be interesting, and I think, you know, for my audience, the people who watch my shows, which is, you know, women 12 to 75, there's something interesting in there for them. CS: And how about the input of the audience? How interested are you in the things where the audience can actually go up to a certain point and then decide, oh wait, I'm going to choose my own adventure. I'm going to run off with Fitz or I'm going to run off with -- SR: Oh, the choose- your-own-adventure stories. I have a hard time with those, and not necessarily because I want to be in control of everything, but because when I'm watching television or I'm watching a movie, I know for a fact that a story is not as good when I have control over exactly what's going to happen to somebody else's character. You know, if I could tell you exactly what I wanted to happen to Walter White, that's great, but the story is not the same, and it's not as powerful. You know, if I'm in charge of how "The Sopranos" ends, then that's lovely and I have an ending that's nice and satisfying, but it's not the same story and it's not the same emotional impact. CS: I can't stop imagining what that might be. Sorry, you're losing me for a minute. SR: But what's wonderful is I don't get to imagine it, because Vince has his own ending, and it makes it really powerful to know that somebody else has told. You know, if you could decide that, you know, in "Jaws," the shark wins or something, it doesn't do what it needs to do for you. The story is the story that is told, and you can walk away angry and you can walk away debating and you can walk away arguing, but that's why it works. That is why it's art. Otherwise, it's just a game, and games can be art, but in a very different way. CS: Gamers who actually sell the right to sit there and comment on what's happening, to me that's more community than storytelling. SR: And that is its own form of campfire. I don't discount that as a form of storytelling, but it is a group form, I suppose. CS: All right, what about the super-super -- the fact that everything's getting shorter, shorter, shorter. And, you know, Snapchat now has something it calls shows that are one minute long. SR: It's interesting. Part of me thinks it sounds like commercials. I mean, it does -- like, sponsored by. But part of me also gets it completely. There's something really wonderful about it. If you think about a world in which most people are watching television on their phones, if you think about a place like India,
Y te enamoras de él mientras lo hace... desde una pantalla de TV. Imagínate sentada junto a él o estar con un personaje como Huck quien está a punto de ejecutar a alguien. Y en lugar de tener una escena donde él le habla a otro personaje muy rápidamente, vaya a un armario y gire hacia ti y te diga, lo que va a pasar y por qué tiene miedo y está nervioso. Es un poco más como el teatro y no estoy segura de que funcione, pero me fascina el concepto y lo que significaría para la audiencia. Y poder jugar con esas ideas sería interesante. ¿Sabes? Creo que para mi audiencia, la gente que mira mis programas, mujeres de 12 a 75 años, hay algo interesante allí para ellas. CS: ¿Qué hay de la opinión de la audiencia? ¿Qué tanto te interesan las cosas donde la audiencia puede hasta cierto punto decidir sus propias aventuras. Si prefieren a Fitz o si prefieren a... SR: Ah, historias donde uno elige sus aventuras. Me han costado trabajo esas, no necesariamente porque quiera tener control de todo, sino porque cuando veo la TV o estoy viendo una película, sé muy bien que una historia no es tan buena cuando tengo el control sobre lo que quiero que le ocurra al personaje de otra persona. ¿Sabes? Podría decirte exactamente lo quería que le ocurriera a Walter White, y está bien, pero la historia no es la misma y no es tan poderosa. Si estoy a cargo de cómo termina "Los Soprano", entonces es encantador, tengo un final agradable y satisfactorio, pero no es la misma historia y no tiene el mismo impacto emocional. CS: No puedo dejar de imaginar cómo sería. Lo siento, estoy yendo un poco lejos. SR: Lo asombroso es que no logro imaginarlo, porque Vince tiene su propio final, y el que otra persona lo haya decidido lo hace realmente poderoso. ¿Sabes? Si uno decidiera eso, en "Tiburón", el tiburón ganaría, no tendría el mismo efecto. Es la historia es la historia que se cuenta y puedes enojarte o puedes dudar de ella y puedes discutir, pero así funciona. Por eso es arte. De otra manera, sería solo un juego, y los juegos pueden ser arte, pero de manera muy diferente. CS: Los videojugadores que venden el derecho de sentarse ahí y comentar lo que ocurre para mí es más una comunidad que una narración. SR: Y esa es su propia manera de reunirse. No descarto que sea una forma de narración pero es un formato grupal, supongo. CS: Muy bien, ¿qué hay del súper-súper... el hecho de que todo sea más y más breve. Ahora, Snapchat tiene programas que duran un minuto. SR: Es interesante. Una parte de mí piensa que parecen comerciales. Es decir, lo son, tienen patrocinador. Pero una parte de mí lo comprende completamente. Hay algo realmente asombroso en ello. Si piensas que hay un mundo en que la mayoría de las personas mira TV en sus teléfonos, si piensas en lugares como India, donde más se transmite y donde más se mira, lo más breve tiene sentido. Si se le puede cobrar a la gente más dinero por menos contenido,
some distributor has figured out a way to make a lot more money. If you're making content, it costs less money to make it and put it out there. And, by the way, if you're 14 and have a short attention span, like my daughter,
el distribuidor ha encontrado una manera de hacer mucho más dinero. Si uno crea contenido, cuesta menos dinero hacerlo y publicarlo. Y, por cierto, alguien de 14 años y un corto periodo de atención, como mi hija,
that's what you want to see, that's what you want to make, that's how it works.
quiere ver eso, quieres producir eso, así funciona.
And if you do it right and it actually feels like narrative, people will hang on for it no matter what you do. CS: I'm glad you raised your daughters, because I am wondering how are they going to consume entertainment, and also not just entertainment, but news, too. When they're not -- I mean, the algorithmic robot overlords are going to feed them what they've already done. How do you think we will correct for that and make people well-rounded citizens? SR: Well, me and how I correct for it is completely different than how somebody else might do it. CS: Feel free to speculate. SR: I really don't know how we're going to do it in the future. I mean, my poor children have been the subject of all of my experiments. We're still doing what I call "Amish summers" where I turn off all electronics and pack away all their computers and stuff and watch them scream for a while until they settle down into, like, an electronic-free summer. But honestly, it's a very hard world
Y si lo haces bien y realmente parece una narración, las personas se engancharán sin importar lo que uno haga. CS: Me alegra que hayas criado a tus hijas, porque me pregunto cómo consumirán ellas entretenimiento, y no solo entretenimiento, las noticias también. Cuando los señores supremos algorítmicos proveen lo mismo. ¿Cómo corregiremos eso para lograr ciudadanos plenos? SR: Bueno, cómo lo corrijo yo es algo completamente diferente de cómo lo haría otra persona. CS: Siéntete libre de especular. SR: No sé cómo lo haremos en el futuro, en realidad. Mis hijas han pasado por todos mis experimentos. Aún hacemos lo que llamo "veranos amish" porque desconecto todo electrónico, guardo sus computadoras y cosas y las miro enloquecer un rato hasta resignarse en un verano libre de electrónicos. Pero honestamente es un mundo muy difícil
in which now, as grown-ups, we're so interested in watching our own thing, and we don't even know that we're being fed, sometimes, just our own opinions. You know, the way it's working now, you're watching a feed, and the feeds are being corrected so that you're only getting your own opinions and you're feeling more and more right about yourself. So how do you really start to discern? It's getting a little bit disturbing. So maybe it'll overcorrect, maybe it'll all explode, or maybe we'll all just become -- I hate to be negative about it, but maybe we'll all just become more idiotic. (Cyndi laughs) CS: Yeah, can you picture any corrective that you could do with scripted, fictional work? SR: I think a lot about the fact that television has the power to educate people in a powerful way, and when you're watching television -- for instance, they do studies about medical shows. I think it's 87 percent, 87 percent of people get most of their knowledge about medicine and medical facts from medical shows, much more so than they do from their doctors, than from articles. So we work really hard to be accurate, and every time we make a mistake, I feel really guilty, like we're going to do something bad, but we also give a lot of good medical information. There are so many other ways to give information on those shows. People are being entertained and maybe they don't want to read the news, but there are a lot of ways to give fair information out on those shows, not in some creepy, like, we're going to control people's minds way, but in a way that's sort of very interesting and intelligent and not about pushing one side's version or the other, like, giving out the truth. It would be strange, though, if television drama was how we were giving the news. CS: It would be strange, but I gather a lot of what you've written as fiction has become prediction this season? SR: You know, "Scandal" has been very disturbing for that reason. We have this show that's about politics gone mad, and basically the way we've always told the show -- you know, everybody pays attention to the papers. We read everything. We talk about everything. We have lots of friends in Washington. And we'd always sort of done our show as a speculation. We'd sit in the room and think, what would happen if the wheels came off the bus and everything went crazy? And that was always great, except now it felt like the wheels were coming off the bus and things were actually going crazy, so the things that we were speculating were really coming true. I mean, our season this year was going to end with the Russians controlling the American election, and we'd written it, we'd planned for it, it was all there, and then the Russians were suspected of being involved in the American election and we suddenly had to change what we were going to do for our season.
en el que ahora, como adultos, solo nos interesa mirar lo propio, y no sabemos que estamos cerrados en nuestras opiniones nada más. Hoy en día miras una noticia, y la fuente de noticias se corrige para que solo veas tus propias ideas y sientes cada vez que estás más en lo correcto. ¿Cómo puede uno discernir? Es un tanto alarmante. Así que quizá sobrecorrija, quizá todo explote, o quizá solo nos volvamos... detesto ser negativa al respecto, quizá nos volvamos todos más tontos. (Cindy ríe) CS: Sí, ¿imaginas alguna corrección que puedas hacer a una pieza guionada de ficción? SR: Pienso mucho sobre que la TV puede educar a la gente de manera poderosa, y si miras la TV... por ejemplo, hacen estudios sobre programas médicos. Creo que es un 87 % de la gente que obtiene la mayor parte de su conocimiento sobre medicina de los programas médicos, mucho más de lo que obtienen de sus médicos o de artículos. Trabajamos arduamente para ser precisos, y cuando cometemos un error, me siento muy culpable, como si hiciéramos algo malo, pero también damos mucha buena información médica. Hay otras maneras de dar información en esos programas. Se está educando a la gente y quizá no quieran leer las noticias, pero hay muchas otras maneras de dar información justa en esos programas no de una manera espeluznante como si controláramos el pensamiento, pero de alguna manera es algo muy interesante e inteligente sin hacer a un lado ninguna perspectiva, o proclamando la verdad. Sería extraño, no obstante, si a través de las series dramáticas diéramos las noticias. CS: Sería extraño, pero entiendo que mucho de lo que has escrito como ficción se ha vuelto una predicción esta temporada. SR: ¿Sabes? "Scandal" ha sido muy perturbador por esa razón. Tenemos este programa sobre la política que enloquece, y básicamente la manera de contar... ya sabes, todos prestamos atención a los papeles. Leemos todo. Hablamos de todo. Tenemos muchos amigos en Washington. Y siempre hemos hecho el programa como una especulación. Solemos sentarnos a pensar, ¿y si las llantas se desprendieran del autobús y todo enloqueciera? Siempre fue fantástico excepto que ahora parece como si se hubieran desprendido y todo ha enloquecido, las cosas que especulamos se están volviendo verdad. Nuestra temporada este año iba a terminar con los rusos controlando las elecciones de EE.UU. y lo habíamos escrito y planeado, todo estaba allí, y luego se sospechaba que los rusos estuvieron involucrados en las elecciones y de repente tuvimos que cambiar lo que íbamos a hacer en la temporada.
I walked in and I was like, "That scene where our mystery woman starts speaking Russian? We have to fix that and figure out what we're going to do." That just comes from extrapolating out from what we thought was going to happen, or what we thought was crazy. CS: That's great. So where else in US or elsewhere in the world do you look? Who is doing interesting storytelling right now? SR: I don't know, there's a lot of interesting stuff out there. Obviously British television is always amazing and always does interesting things. I don't get to watch a lot of TV, mainly because I'm busy working. And I pretty much try not to watch very much television at all, even American television, until I'm done with a season, because things start to creep into my head otherwise. I start to wonder, like, why can't our characters wear crowns and talk about being on a throne? It gets crazy. So I try not to watch much until the seasons are over. But I do think that there's a lot of interesting European television out there. I was at the International Emmys and looking around and seeing the stuff that they were showing, and I was kind of fascinated. There's some stuff I want to watch and check out. CS: Can you imagine -- I know that you don't spend a lot of time thinking about tech stuff, but you know how a few years ago we had someone here at TED talking about seeing, wearing Google Glass and seeing your TV shows essentially in your eye? Do you ever fantasize when, you know -- the little girl who sat on the pantry floor in your parents' house, did you ever imagine any other medium? Or would you now? SR: Any other medium. For storytelling, other than books? I mean, I grew up wanting to be Toni Morrison, so no. I mean, I didn't even imagine television. So the idea that there could be some bigger world, some more magical way of making things --- I'm always excited when new technology comes out and I'm always the first one to want to try it.
Entré y me dije: "Esa escena donde la mujer misteriosa empieza a hablar ruso, tenemos que cambiarla y pensar qué vamos a hacer". Eso resulta de extrapolar lo que pensamos que iba a pasar, o lo que creímos alocado. CS: Qué genial. ¿En qué otra parte del mundo buscas, aparte de EE.UU.? ¿Quién está haciendo narraciones interesantes ahora? SR: No lo sé, hay muchas cosas interesantes por ahí. Obviamente la TV británica siempre es sorprendente y siempre hace cosas interesantes. No veo mucha TV, en gran parte porque estoy ocupada trabajando. Y trato de no ver mucha TV, incluso TV de EE.UU. hasta que termino la temporada, porque sino se me meten ideas en la cabeza. Me empiezo a preguntar cosas como "¿por qué nuestros personajes no usan coronas y hablan de tronos?" Enloquezco. Así que trato casi de no ver hasta que termina la temporada. Pero sí creo que hay TV europea muy interesante. Estuve en los Emmys internacionales y vi varias cosas que estaban transmitiendo, y me fascinó. Hay algunas cosas que quisiera ver y revisar. CS: ¿Te imaginas... sé que no piensas mucho tiempo en cosas tecnológicas, pero sabes que hace unos años alguien vino aquí a TED a hablar sobre el ver, portaba lentes de Google y podía ver los programas en los ojos? ¿Tienes fantasías sobre... la niña sentada en el piso en la casa de tus padres, has imaginado algún otro medio? ¿O lo harías ahora? SR: ¿Otro medio, para narrar, aparte de los libros? Crecí queriendo ser Toni Morrison, así que no. Ni siquiera imaginé la televisión. La idea de que puede haber un mundo más grande, una manera mágica de hacer cosas... siempre me emociono con lo nuevo de la tecnología y siempre soy la primera en querer probarlo.
The possibilities feel endless and exciting right now, which is what excites me. We're in this sort of Wild West period, to me, it feels like, because nobody knows what we're going to settle on. You can put stories anywhere right now and that's cool to me, and it feels like once we figure out how to get the technology and the creativity of storytelling to meet, the possibilities are endless. CS: And also the technology has enabled the thing I briefly flew by earlier, binge-viewing, which is a recent phenomenon, since you've been doing shows, right? And how do you think does that change the storytelling process at all? You always had a bible for the whole season beforehand, right? SR: No, I just always knew where we were going to end. So for me, the only way I can really comment on that is that I have a show that's been going on for 14 seasons and so there are the people who have been watching it for 14 seasons, and then there are the 12-year-old girls I'd encounter in the grocery store who had watched 297 episodes in three weeks. Seriously, and that's a very different experience for them, because they've been inside of something really intensely for a very short period of time in a very intense way, and to them the story has a completely different arc and a completely different meaning because it never had any breaks. CS: It's like visiting a country and then leaving it. It's a strange -- SR: It's like reading an amazing novel and then putting it down. I think that is the beauty of the experience. You don't necessarily have to watch something for 14 seasons. It's not necessarily the way everything's supposed to be. CS: Is there any topic that you don't think we should touch? SR: I don't think I think of story that way. I think of story in terms of character and what characters would do
Las posibilidades son infinitas y emocionantes ahora, y eso me emociona. Estamos en esta especie de Lejano Oeste y siento... que nadie sabe cómo terminará todo. Hoy puedes hacer historias acerca de todo y eso me gusta, y parece como si, una vez que averigüemos cómo juntar la tecnología y la creatividad, las posibilidades serán infinitas. CS: Y la tecnología también ha permitido lo que sugerí hace un momento, atracones televisivos, un fenómeno reciente, desde que empezaste a hacer programas ¿no? ¿Cómo crees que eso cambia el proceso narrativo? Siempre tuviste una biblia durante toda la temporada, ¿no? SR: No, simplemente siempre supe cómo iba a terminar. Así que para mí, lo único que puedo comentar al respecto es que tengo un programa que ha existido por 14 temporadas y hay gente que lo ha estado mirando durante las 14 temporadas, y hay chicas de 12 años que he encontrado en el supermercado que han mirado 297 episodios en tres semanas. En serio, y esa es una experiencia muy distinta para ellas, porque han estado dentro de algo muy intensamente durante un periodo muy corto de tiempo de manera muy intensa, y para ellas la historia tiene un arco completamente diferente y un significado muy distinto porque nunca se ha interrumpido. CS: Es como visitar un país para luego marcharse. Es extraño... SR: Es como leer una novela estupenda y después dejarla. Creo que esa es la belleza de esta experiencia. No necesitas mirar algo durante 14 temporadas. No tiene que ser necesariamente de esa manera. CS: ¿Hay algún tema que creas que no debamos tocar? SR: No veo la narración de esa manera. Pienso en la historia en términos de personajes y lo que harían
and what characters need to do in order to make them move forward, so I'm never really thinking of story in terms of just plot, and when writers come into my writer's room and pitch me plot, I say, "You're not speaking English." Like, that's the thing I say. We're not speaking English. I need to hear what's real. And so I don't think of it that way. I don't know if there's a way to think there's something I wouldn't do because that feels like I'm plucking pieces of plot off a wall or something. CS: That's great. To what extent do you think you will use -- You know, you recently went on the board of Planned Parenthood and got involved in the Hillary Clinton campaign. To what extent do you think you will use your storytelling in the real world to effect change?
y lo que necesitan hacer los personajes para desarrollarse, así que nunca pienso en la historia solo en términos de su trama, cuando los escritores vienen a mi oficina y me lanzan su trama les digo, "No estás hablando de verdad". Les digo eso. No estamos hablando de verdad. Necesito escuchar lo real. Así que no lo pienso así. No sé si existe una forma de pensar que haya algo que no haría porque sería como arrancar piezas de la trama de un muro. CS: Es genial. ¿Hasta qué punto crees que usarás... recientemente estuviste en el panel de "Planned Parenthood" y te involucraste con la campaña de Hillary Clinton. ¿Hasta qué punto crees que usarás la narración en el mundo real para ejercer un cambio?
SR: Well, you know, there's -- That's an intense subject to me, because I feel like the lack of narrative that a lot of people have is difficult. You know, like, there's a lot of organizations that don't have a positive narrative that they've created for themselves that would help them.
SR: Bueno, sabes, hay... Es un tema intenso para mí, porque siento que la escasez de narración en mucha gente es difícil. ¿Sabes? Es como si hubiera muchas organizaciones que no tienen una narración positiva porque no la han creado para sí, para ayudarse.
There's a lot of campaigns that could be helped with a better narrative. The Democrats could do a lot
Hay muchas campañas a las que les iría bien con una mejor narración. Los demócratas podrían hacer mucho
with a very strong narrative for themselves. There's a lot of different things that could happen in terms of using storytelling voice, and I don't mean that in a fiction way, I mean that in a same way that any speechwriter would mean it. And I see that, but I don't necessarily know that that's, like, my job to do that. CS: All right. Please help me thank Shonda. SR: Thank you. (Applause)
con una narración fuerte para sí. Podrían ocurrir muchas cosas diferentes al usar la voz de la narración, y no me refiero a hacerlo en forma de ficción, sino en la misma manera en que lo haría un escritor de discursos. Y veo eso, pero no sé si necesariamente ese sería mi trabajo. CS: Muy bien. Por favor, démosle las gracias a Shonda. SR: Gracias. (Aplausos)